uh okay let's uh get started so uh let's
finish this uh calculation last time uh
we're talking about uh still the system
of important and so
um we are working with
um the usual uh
uh like so
um and then um we uh we're performing a
liquidation so you feed to uh
and uh
it defines with uh
M squared
about
Omega squared 2 is greater
um and the quality is that the the
observable that we're interested uh in
uh competing uh was uh this quantity uh
the ground state uh
Q hat p q hat zero
um and then uh we uh once again in this
um
T going to minus type how is a
hypotheist so T had that negative the
negative imaginary number
um wrote this as uh let me for now just
uh indicate just to avoid unnecessary
confusion I call this ge often I will
drop this with this uh this uh super
script uh so the GE is related to G uh
binary equation P equal into minus sign
power
but anyway I can write this in this in
this way still
um
I'm just going to write this as two
halves it's really repeat now
um
um and uh and we said that uh the reason
that we wanted to uh write it this way
is because uh once we uh have done the
with rotation uh it's uh there's a
convenient uh path in the world uh
expression for this in terms of
QuickBooks in that we don't actually
have to uh uh specify the boundary
condition he says we can take this limit
uh t uh going to
um technological Divinity uh where we
add
um
this uh
it's about minus on the page bar s uh
including
being the integral in this example I'm
taking the range actually minus t to
capital P from uh vital of uh with l
uh Oblivion uh as a function of
qren over there
um and uh with the insertion of Q uh Tau
Cube zero
um uh and uh
is it the same thing but without that a
circuit
do I have last time and uh then we're in
the middle of doing this calculation
um
time but that would uh to be the purpose
of this in this sense we uh decide that
we want to use a different way to
represent the the functional integral so
that is we expanded the QR Tau
the boundary condition doesn't matter
but if I were to do a calculation of
this quantity I'd find it before I take
the limit I still have to specify the
boundary condition and last time
um the way I said that we're going to
specify the boundary condition we could
say that
so as we go from -15 it is
um this view is that the queue of power
isn't a typically zero and endpoints
right so uh and with that we can expand
on the four-year basis and from one to
Infinity uh q n and n sub Tau and uh
is normalized in the way I explained it
last time so and hi uh K over to t uh
and then
the internet access in terms of this uh
just plug in and calculate and with the
straightforward calculation
um and the result is a sum from remote
stands from expand from one to Infinity
uh so one half is a potential return
uh Omega squared with the right it will
the cube now score just becomes sum over
again squared and the kinetic
environment gives uh n pi over 2T
this way
so so once we have that uh we are then
ready to to take this and plug into that
formula uh and and then these uh the
cube tile and q0 over here we can just
again expand in terms of the qns and
this event this comes along with the
right
um and so uh really uh these qns These
are the integration variables in this
functional integral so we just need to
perform uh the integration the scale
change across so we just need to study
the integral of for example
n
um uh there's good I read the romance of
visibility
there are no constraints on these
copages other than the real parameters
um uh and uh e to the minus one over
H bar uh let's say you look at the term
that is depend on two n so let's look at
that a particular term like so
um
uh well actually let me just spread it
this action is Manifest me uh
positive evidence
the function of the qns
um and uh if you have uh if you have now
so so this will be one of the factors
the numerator you have the similar thing
you can have some uh insertion so you
may have uh
one or or or or qn or maybe qn Square
when we expand this cute talk it's zero
um
okay so so of course if you have one
discussing integral you have qn uh then
this this integround is off so we've
just got zero and squared uh you get
something uh we're gonna calculate
um but uh uh a little bit right over
here so the uh
it's uh it's not hard to see that
um so
let's say this guy let me write this
here
zero
um
calculate uh let me use it in the
patient this uh q and qn expression
value this is just uh uh you know
product so I've now replaced that uh
measure by just the product of uh dqn
from one to Infinity uh there might be
some overall Dimension constants uh
which I will not care about for this
purpose because that's whatever it is
it's going to be cancel between the
numerator and economy
um so I have in the numerator and this
uh e to the minus one of H bar and let's
say
and with a q n q n is actually I'm
definitely expecting value so so
um I'm gonna divide by the integral
um
about
without any section
uh as you can see
um okay right so so that's all that's
needed uh to calculate this and then the
result of this is just going to be a
limited Infinity of that it's the value
of Q and qn times uh F and now
yeah
um what does like bracket q and qn
what's the definition
this is a trivial trivia
and really funny this whole thing is the
expectation value so you think of this
this integral as a sensor for uh you
know this is something e to the minus
actually the sum weighting factor and
we're just sampling over it's not
impossible uh values of qn and
calculates with this weight the
expression value of the product the
quantity q and QX oh this is just just
the definition
uh okay so but let's let's focus on this
one this is all we need to know in order
to get to the get to the answer where we
care about
any questions yes why do we like why can
we pick a particular event and um
uh because it's only about the salvation
over a pole and uh yes we do uh yes and
uh
sorry ah okay sorry that's what that was
the time okay
thank you
okay uh yes
I agree that what we have is awesome
he's going to imaginary time when we
expect it can be exponential in the in
English uh good question uh this is a
very important point I want to clarify
uh when I draw uh what cute cow is this
has nothing to do with the time
Evolution I think about the question the
most right so uh the Q tau is arbitrary
integration variable uh there's no
constraint until apart from the boundary
condition so nobody did I say that you
have to pay any kind of equations there
is no such a sound
this F of NFL these are arbitrary based
the functions the only they're only
subject to the constraint that they have
to vanish and the two endpoints the
minus C and T that is the only only uh
only constraint
that's the rule of the pattern right
nowhere did I say use the word equation
of motion the question motion
exactly what it means well you you will
see it but so far there's no there's no
need to mention such such words that's
cute it's just some uh integration
variable nothing more than that
so imagine this last time but maybe it
was a little bit quick I'm assuming I'm
setting q0 and sorry Q minus P minus t
to zero and also set a Q Plus E3 so this
is my q i I call it Qi this is qf right
that's the initial and final division
but that was the arbitrary I I could
have changed this is zero to uh whatever
whatever number right I want the whole
point is that it won't matter uh as long
as I choose it through the same but I'm
going straight in the numerator and
denominator that was the whole point of
the derivation last time right when we
show that as you take the limit other
people Infinity you always project onto
the ground state so as long as you're
interested in the ground state
especially Mattingly
or later it would be causing this no
vacuum that certain value the ground
state has been value
for the which one thing happening bro
they're not even sure it won't matter
well we'll say that expressly so so far
obviously everything depends on capital
T but we'll see that there's a
well-defined articles in better limits
we're in the T dependence will drop out
any other questions yes
uh yes it is uh that's about this okay
okay doesn't matter
okay uh
uh so
um
um okay so what is this well uh
obviously uh if uh if n is not equal to
n this is uh this is going to be equal
to zero
a factor that's like this with a single
insertion or qn and not zero because
it's integrated on
uh so uh the only situation you have to
worry about uh is uh when n is equal to
n in which case uh you can just easily
calculate this galaxy integral with the
Q and squared insertion and the final
answer I'll just write down the answer
so
that's a good something so uh so the
conclusion is that this uh equation
value
and command is equal to uh chronic or
Delta in n and n so when m equal to n it
is a h bar over uh
calculus
I don't know how to do that integral uh
any questions about this so far
um so so with this uh then uh we uh we
have the answer so let's plug in and uh
and look at that uh
coordinate function
so uh the quantities that they call
um
um well in fact uh it's uh just for the
sake of discussion let me consider
something uh slightly more General
um so uh let me consider
um
let's add uh Title One and uh file two
um perhaps a slightly okay notation I
didn't want to introduce new notation
but uh you know whenever I write
later because so far once I have done
the reputation I'm always writing
keywords just a functional top and
hopefully you remember where it comes
um
so
uh so this uh would be uh according to
what we wrote over there
um uh this was it's about to be the
limit of the figures Infinity of sum
over n and M Run 1 to Infinity uh this
uh
qn u n value and a one again
um and uh uh so let me just one more
steps because Infinity of the following
uh so uh now n had to be equal to M for
this would be not zero so I just have
sum over n one definite d uh I've got
this Factor H bar over
and pi over uh two t squared plus Omega
squared uh and then I I have f n Tau 1 f
n Tau two uh now let me plug into it
plugging the expression at ends on God's
uh one over t
uh sine of n i l one plus capital T over
2T times sine uh another n pi
foreign uh Q at QE at R1 is
uh yes uh yes now you you uh one should
be a slightly uh careful about this so
um uh you know usually what I really
demand is expression uh is that you um
take uh uh zero Q hat T1 you have P2 uh
this was the two point function because
G of T1 and D2 and another we continue
to function to T equals to minus Title
One and into one not two minus one I
want e to those two minus five two uh
now you could try to do this directly at
level of the operator uh but uh to do
that it had to be a little bit careful
because uh this my spoil some of the
standard assumptions you might make
about this operator so for example
um
mentioned
unique uh
and I'll do it around that's right but
we pass out here
um and um uh so so they can say that the
skill has now uh would be a CEO would be
still replaced by minus I found so this
becomes these are the uh one over
uh
actually let's make sure
yes one number H bar H hat hotel uh Q
hat zero e to the minus one over or you
can't now
um uh and uh if you take this and plug
into this query function uh that's
actually correct but you have to be a
little careful for example
um uh this operator I like that one uh
for real how it would not be permission
anymore right so usually we say that the
skill had T in quantum mechanics right
for ENT is a permission operator and
that is that is true that property is
invariant under time Evolution if it
will evolved by this there's no
permission because because the hermitian
can't hear that this is
the same expression
um uh but that's not true
okay so so
careful enough but then then yes you can
you can just take it you have a towel
and do certain things but but if you get
confused you should always think in
terms of original know two points for
your function in real time and follow
this analog continuation procedure this
will be quite important when we discuss
uh we discussed the anonymously
important field Theory later
um uh by the end the case uh as you
recorded last time uh the job of this
for the moment is to is that the capture
some information about the spectrum of
the theory that's why we're interested
in it so if you get confused you can
always go back to uh this representation
of this in terms of the energy
eigensterase that I wrote last time uh
and uh and and understand the meaning of
of this quantity we're trying to compute
any other questions
um okay so so now let's let's calculate
this let's quantity in the Picos
independent limit so so if uh everything
we're saying so far makes sense
of limits should be well defined this
expression looks a bit complicated
um so let's uh let's investigate what it
is in the uh
that
thank you
um so as you might expect uh
if you
in real time
it's no longer coaches for example
foreign
um because before you take the limits uh
we're not projecting onto the ground
state
and so so there's no reason to think
that it's time translation variants
but um
any other questions
um okay so so let's take the limit
because Infinity how do we take the
limit well as you uh might imagine uh
the sound has a chemical integral
somehow
um so in fact uh but let's see so uh
let's look at this point here is here
uh this and pi over 2T uh this little N
is a sum over all positive integers uh
and so when the capital t is very large
then this becomes very density space
um there's a kind of some kind of
continuous variable I'm going to Define
this to be okay and so the idea is that
the sum Over N is supposedly but with
what measure well let's let's see so
um so the point is that this if we
Define this would be k then pi over 2T
right
any uh questions about this
um so uh so then uh with this uh it's uh
they're pretty easy to turn this
left-hand side well between this button
here uh into uh uh continue from the
left left side of the board
okay so continue from the left side of
the board right uh so this is now
becomes an integral uh integral of what
so so
Decay from zero to Infinity
um I have to compensate uh with uh so
the sum will become 2T over pi times
this integral but then I have to
multiply this H bar divided by D so D
pencil you get two H bar I
um and then uh this one over this factor
is just one over uh K squared plus Omega
squared to have that
and then have the two signs so the sign
becomes
uh sign of uh M pile original view
that's K so sine of uh K uh cell one
plus T and the sine of uh okay
uh Tau two plus three
also had to take limit T equals to
Infinity because then the GE is still
yeah it does make you feel uncomfortable
but we'll see what happens
okay so so it just turns into this
integral yes before we're using the
limited synchross Infinity to turn you
know that quantity
should have already evaluated uh well uh
the claim uh not quite because uh uh you
know you can't literally substitute the
Stick Of The Infinity in the in the sign
uh because uh uh well
um
uh
well I I guess you know if you're
writing such a way to eliminate then you
could but so far I'm not I'm not doing
that
um uh I mean uh I suppose you you could
have done that but it won't matter for
our purpose
um so uh
um you know you can you can you can take
the speed to be some arbitrary a large
constants and take this into Infinity
for the rest of this point in Paris and
then take this at the end it's not
actually going to make a difference in
the answer but uh I suppose you could
also uh you know uh laboriously uh you
know I guess depend on where they're
standing even or are they rewrite this
signs of the cosines
but you know the answer will be the
second one
foreign
expression uh so we can perform this
integral by uh there's a standard trick
to do this but but we're going to
rewrite this in terms of
um explanations so so rewrite uh
that's I uh in terms of
uh the explanation of things like e to
the I okay
here we'll have a possibly this time
okay two
okay uh so here you will see uh terms
involving Tau y minus how two and also
Tan One Plus Tau two plus two t
all right so so all we need to do is to
calculate some kind of uh
Decay with this exponential function in
k
uh this kind of integral is something
that will encounter over and over again
in this course so I'm going to go
through it uh once for all and how to
calculate this because now of course you
you might just look up some I don't know
mathematical handbook or with
Mathematica which will tell you the
answer
um but uh but there's a useful trick to
use to calculate this kind of integrals
that will come up over and over again so
I want to explain uh explain a Little
Dream let's consider
um uh the integral uh oh by the way
before that let me looks nice
modification so the integrand is uh even
functioning okay obviously so I'm going
to double the integral multiplicity and
Factor one half so that's the same thing
uh
okay Tau just considered as an example
because they're all going to be of this
form
over K squared plus a negative squared
so once we know how to do this is
up there
um
okay so
so uh the the way that is totally useful
for us to for evaluating integers of
this type which I understand it will
come up over and over again
um these two uh
view this uh view this
um has a contour
uh integral
uh
uh a polymorphic function
so we're gonna once again
um consider now this is the 50 Grand
and function okay the first thing we
observe is the integrand is a analytic
function of K that can actually be and
they can continue until the entire
complex play except we're composed
so
um if you take the 50 Grand and uh
continue to the higher complex so this
is the complex
this is the real axis and this is the
imaginary okay
access and um
and our integration
is performed
by
uh
by integrating along the real
along the real actions
we're going to do this integral as a
counter integral
any questions so far so far in this let
me know anything uh so the idea is that
we want to simplify integral by
deforming accountable now a basic
property of uh
the version of a homework function is
that the integration of another function
so allow any close uh Contour is zero so
this is uh everyone familiar with this
fact so this is one of the most basic
facts of complex analysis uh in one
variable uh so so that means the result
of this integral that doesn't change if
I deform the Contour to something like
this okay the indoor is exactly the same
uh provided that the function so the
requirements that often has to be uh
complex analytics in between
uh now if you look at this function it
is going to be analytic indeed except uh
when the denominator vanishes right so
it's got um
the function here
as a whole post at k equals plus minus
Pi Omega and I say and the function in
complex K so the both are here and here
so this is I okay sorry I Omega
so we're allowed to people when we come
to arbitrary won't change the result of
the integral uh unless you get past this
hole
uh there's another way equipment to say
it okay so before that then we say that
um if you didn't have this all uh if you
are able to expose the conquer all the
way to Infinity
um then you see uh suppose so I didn't
say anything about the sign of Tau so
assume that assume that power is real
which is the case for our application
here right so uh on two cases either tau
is positive
negative these two cases of Interest
um now if tau is positive right uh if
you send uh K to the manual if you send
the imaginary part of K to Infinity
uh then e to the i k Tau will be
exponentially suppressed
right so so if power is positive if you
push the counter all the way up uh it
will be uh you know just got zero zero
uh instead of equivalently there's
another way to say this sometimes we'll
say that we can close the Contour on the
other half plane so when I draw this
yellow Arc the bigger the little Arc is
that
uh infinite uh distance
um so the contribution if it tells
greater than zero
uh is going to be negligible as you push
the arc to Infinity
right so um so in that case uh you might
as well calculate the total uh integral
along the Green Path together with the
yellow Arc and that is a closed Contour
uh and with the clothes Contour you can
it have been a call the result will just
be zero
but it's because of the code you can
stream the sound color uh
um it's ready to conquer off of the onto
this running the hole without changing
the integral and the result of that is
just the residue of the function uh at
the ball
right so the the conclusion is that uh
by this by this argument
um
we
look at that uh let me just right here
now the conclusion of this argument uh
is that
um
uh for
Tau positive
um the the integral
uh
this integral is equal to uh two Pi the
revenue there and says
k equals to the pole uh into the I take
it out
um and um
uh
uh and there's this residue is a
straight word to calculate for example
you can write this as the e to the ik
tell over
The Edge plus minus sign oh my God okay
plus I Omega to take the radio just
means that you you strip up this strip
of this strip of this factor and for the
rest you send okay to I Omega
so the result of this is then equal to
uh pi over Omega e to the minus
Omega power
any questions about that that's the
result of this integral
yes I can explain why the upper like
curve would give you zero like I guess
like powers and imaginary so when K
becomes very large
I'm assuming right so that was positive
um so if you're way up there uh it's
suppressed because it's it's much
suppressed uh okay so yeah so K is a
matter of reasons okay okay has a large
imaginary parts right right okay and if
you're out there in this direction yeah
uh it's gonna be suppressed because it's
economic So Soft so whatever which are
you working you go again you estimate
the country from different sections of
art but it's just gonna it's just gonna
be zero
um
so so that's the results again it's very
simple result
um and uh you can repeat the accent the
the analysis so so this this argument uh
uh this argument doesn't apply for Tau
negative okay because for tell negative
this it doesn't manage the desire kind
of blows up
um so that'll be the value of the
function blows up so
um if uh
uh if tile is a negative uh you have to
do something different you have to close
uh below
I'm going to go this way from now you
have to
go to Contour on a lower half plane
in which case uh you get the revenue
here but with a minus sign because of
the orientation the counter runs counter
clock so it runs the clockwise uh and uh
if you if you do that calculation uh
you'll find that before uh Tau negative
uh you know the the result of this uh
this integral is uh minus two Pi I of
the revenue uh uh
minus I Omega the same function here
foreign
okay so uh we're not quite done we're
almost done so the ones we have this
gonna plug into that and uh we're gonna
find
here's the following
as you take this limit
uh here are you going to get friends
like this
right so some of the terms evolve into
the ik tell what minus how two so I want
to help you with the difference uh the
other terms will give you is things like
e to the ik Taiwan plus 100 plus plus
two t so you're gonna have here L1 plus
Alpha plus two t by the way between the
infinity so that term will just drop out
and deliver people
using this formula you'll find the
result is H bar over to Omega e to the
minus Omega Tau y minus
that's our final results
and remember what this is where we're
covering
okay so now if you uh recall uh this uh
one of the world last time concerned
with decomposing this in terms of
insertion of a complete basis of
energizing States uh the coefficient
here tell us about the gap between the
excited the energy difference the
exciting States and the ground state so
here are the only contribution we see is
Omega this Omega you recognize as the
gap between the first exciting state of
the harmonious and the ground
now vaporizer has some arbitrary
operator not just q but some maybe some
polynomial here let's say Insertion I
could also find other exciting States
but in this case stand for some due to
some accidents of the harmonic offset
they're actually Q back on the ground
state as you probably know it's only
involved the first excited state this is
the accident for the harmonic but more
General lagrangea system that would not
be true
in this case because this guy here
only overlap with the first excited
States we only find This this term
evolving
Omega itself which is the gap between
the earth exactly State and the ground
state
any questions about this example
now by the way let me just say that of
course if you have this in this case
because the formula is so simple it's
trivial to elegant video back to the
real time if you wish but uh you know
I'll let you figure out the signs yes
[Music]
that is correct uh while this explain
was what we plan to begin this was there
was a well-defined expression and uh
right in terms of well I mean you know
you know how to compute this using uh
the wave function you can just write a
great round State weight function like
we're going to calculate this as some
integral and you'll find the same kinds
of your check for yourself
oh uh right I mean of course the kind of
being killed you might worry that we
dropped on infinite uh constant Factor
but it's always a cancer between the
numerator and economy right so here
we're covering some kind of expression
value so for this purpose I don't have
to be too careful about the content that
modifies this measure pack now in the
homework problem you have to calculate
now the expanded value by the partition
function the homework problem number two
and for that purpose you actually have
to keep track of all normalization so so
so that's a bit more subtle but uh
any other questions
all right
um so
um
uh so it was nice that it worked out but
uh but it was a pain
uh and uh now I'm going to introduce a
bit of uh
some simple uh technique allow us to
simplify such computation so we don't
have to go through this exercise uh
over and over
um
uh so uh you see uh in the end of the
day we're just doing some Galaxy
integral in this editing this simple
example we're doing a Galaxy integral
um and uh um it's useful to uh have a
efficient way to calculate this kind of
experience values in the Galaxy video so
I'm going to first describe a
mathematical formula for calculating
equation values back to gaussian
integral that's very easy to uh to to
understand uh and then we're gonna later
we'll see the application of this very
soon see the application
oh um
okay so now
uh so let us consider
um
so consider
a general form of the Galaxy integral in
multivariables
um let's consider the following so the
big thing well the cube Vector says an
n-dimensional Galaxy is equal
um and uh we put the minus something the
something is supposed to be the analog
of this actions euclidean action here
right so I'm going to take this thing to
be so Q is some Vector this Q Vector if
you think of it as an analog of the
collection of all these qms that you
wish
uh so e to the minus the action so it's
action that is going to be one half uh Q
uh trans to both uh multiplying a matrix
a multiplying Q
and so this a
is um
right now let's say a symmetric Matrix
so
um
some symmetric means
so this is the sum over n n a n n like u
n u n
let's assume that
um
uh and uh plus uh so let me say
generalized this by adding a linear term
J back with that with Q back where J
it's an arbitrary vector and I call this
uh the generating function uh Z as a
function in Theta because this is
definition
um okay so this uh we can do uh so I
just write a formula once for all and
and figure out how they can do this but
the result if you didn't have this J
Term uh you just get 2 pi to the N
number two
um one number square root of the
determinants of the Matrix a
the the simple way to do that is to do a
change of variable you change your base
do a linear change the base into queue
to diagonal activations okay that's the
simplest way to derive this answer
anyway that's the answer for the Galaxy
if you will if your statutes in zero and
if J is none zero uh you just need to
compute a square and shift the Q and uh
um
square and you can get rid of the
[Music]
a uh a q uh minus uh a uh in verse J
uh and here uh minus uh a inverse J uh
then uh so that will produce this this
linear term in gene q and then you have
to add back in the uh plus I have J
that's both a inverse okay
for this term
you can redefine Q by shifting this away
and suppose
uh a inverse okay
so so that's the result of this
is that the result of this uh
General function of the regarding
any questions so far
straightforward
um so uh given this formula uh if you
have so we're going to be ages if
expanded values like that so I suppose
you have some function f of Q
let's have a few type of analog of this
insertion of the Q hat operators in the
Packer device population
insertions of these q and qns uh some
functional queue and you want to look we
want to calculate the equation value we
increase the value but it is defined to
be uh one over z uh with the J is set to
zero so that's like the pathogrows
without any operating section
um but then we have the pattern to grow
with the insertion so cut into the uh
you
so that that's the action here it's
actually not the path of two
so that's the expression value
calculates
uh but now using this uh gaussian
integral formula
we can
Express the result in terms of this Z of
J
uh so what is that so the result of this
is
um
uh so uh
zero
um so what is that
um well uh you can think of this as
um so how would you how would you relate
to the topics I think something like
this
um if you take a derivative of Z of J
with respect to J
uh you just pull down a insertion of
queue
uh
J twice uh we're back to J twice you
just pull down two factors of Q and so
forth so you can write this this thing
as F of uh
B by D J
derivatives we then set J to zero
uh what do I mean by this uh
or more generally okay they're serious
uh so a function of F is a series
and Q right and uh every time you see a
qn you're replaced by V by DJ that's
what I mean by this this thing so it
turns this function into a some
differential operator which acts on this
DJ you just take you taking derivatives
and after you do that you set J to zero
and then you get this equation back
any question about this
um so here we say the reputational and F
of Q that's definitely the normal cue
that's not been shifted by Chain right
uh this is the definition literally
right this is the defined to be this
experience later we're going to apply
this to uh to the value of operators on
the mechanical system but for now this
is my definition
oh I'm just talking because no there's
no j
so but I can relate it to the thing with
the tag by first starting with your
number J I take derivative and after
after
this exponential of J dot Q goes away
but I'm still definitely the peculiar
surface so the future is just some
arbitrary some some are very parameter
which we use as a tool but at least
just for convenience
oh this is just a simple bookkeeping
device for for activities of calculation
um so uh for example uh let's look at
some examples uh simple examples uh so
uh qn expression value
um now this is just uh
I mean we know this it's just because of
the the integround is the power function
of the view if you have a single q a
circuit but of course you can also see
from here because uh uh the the sky here
if you expand in J is always uh even the
power of J that appears if you take a
single derivative zero other results
so that's of course true
um and if you have a qn commands uh this
is just uh this well let's plug in our
formula
um so
um
so for this uh purpose uh we don't have
to oh worry about this uh determine a
and combined with these factors because
it's going to cancel between here and
here it's just gonna be some Concepts we
don't care about that in this expression
value uh so this point of theory is just
a b by the this formula D by b j n d by
b j m
huh uh potential of one half uh J
transpose inverse Matrix of a what about
J so let me write out the indices so
call it paq so p
now of course this is very easy to
calculate just expand this uh
exponential but there's only one term
that contributes which is the quadratic
which is determining moment or two J's
it's the first time when you expand this
out or contribute
um and uh uh we act on that term these
two dudes you can account either one of
the two J's to get them Factor two the
cancel game exactly like half and you're
just done with a inverse and then
that's good
um
any questions about this
sorry
all of all of these chains yes so that's
that's what I what I meant
the J vectors
um okay so uh let's do a starting one
complicated example
uh there's this uh
electorates will become uh
useful later
um so let's look at four queuing
surgeons uh the three cubic friction
again will give people zero because of
the symmetry of Q goes to minus q but
let's look at the fourth two
instructions so so this would be uh
uh
d by D okay n d by b k m
d by d j r d j s of e to the one half J
transpose a inverse J transpose with a j
zero
okay uh so of course the only term that
will contribute
is uh
uh the thing that's
quadratic in the exponents so one over
two factorial so let's bring
it
it's just that
now of course you can you know calculate
that uh but uh I'm going to uh draw a
picture that represents this uh that
will help us uh keep track of the the
commentatorics
[Music]
um
well actually for this purpose maybe a
bit of Overkill but I will draw this
picture anyway
um so it's kind of a useful uh way to
think about the common Turks okay so so
um let's write this as
uh so there's some backup one house
because I have a 1 8 here number eight
times something
uh what do we have uh well there are
various ways the derivative can act on
this case
um so uh several times I will specialize
especially how we do the sound or just a
moment
um now uh so I'm going to representative
with the external line here it's in the
stand and uh and uh r and s
um
and uh the stuff uh oh sorry this is the
transverse here
right so
um here uh
uh every time I have a fact of the this
J A inverse J I'm going to represent
this by uh a Vertex with two lines
coming out
um and then
you know this by a inverse uh with the
in the sense that uh you know if I take
the derivative all I need to do is to
connect uh connect the uh the lines
so
um
um so for example uh if I take this
derivative on that I connect this line
then take this derivative of that Jack
like this line and I read out the result
a inverse NR for the result okay so I
just need to look at all the possible
way to connect these blue lines uh to
the white lines for example uh here is a
way to do it like like this I can
connect this with that stick like this
with that and this is one connect and
then you can do whatever way you want so
here the sum is all possible all
possible
uh
uh ways
to connect
the the right line to the Bulldogs right
uh and uh and how many ways did they
have and in this case the the number is
uh equal to four factors
four different ways to
um the permutation of the four uh four
legs
um and uh uh so uh so in total uh you
will end up with uh uh 24 terms here but
there's a pack of one over eight and in
fact uh there are only three different
types of terms and if you respect this
it's not hard to convince yourself the
result is just a inverse and M
a inverse RS plus uh some permutations a
inverse uh and r
a inverse and I guess
um and Q and universities and R right so
so that's the results
um
uh uh I collect every white line to
every blue line and once I connect them
that's that's gone and I connected the
remaining so so I have to connect since
I have to pair up is that there's white
lines with the blue lines Why do I have
to do that because I'm taking derivative
this is
this can be connected to any one of them
any one of the white lines right so okay
I can connect this to any one of these
white lines let me remember the fact
that this derivative fact on each of
these drapes and it will give a
contribution
so so this is just how you take a
derivative it's nothing so so the result
is uh the sum of these three times
uh any questions so far yes so how would
so like the the specific one you draw
correspond to one term yeah yeah that's
what
it's on this one there eight uh
identical contributions
contribution for example uh you can you
can switch the video around and it's the
same and the answer is the same but
there is another term
so I'm just saying that until the a
program you have 1 8 times 24 terms but
that's inconsistent with that actually
end up with three times like this
um
uh but in fact uh you can uh this is
actually uh incredible Overkill Because
the actual answer is a much simpler way
to to phrase the answer so let me just
explain that
um so you can calculate the usually
uh you can generalize this example and
derive a rule for calculating the
equation value in this respect to the
calcium integral of the arbitrary number
of hue insertions as follows so
um generally uh we have a Q and Q and Q
R let me know whatever
so when you have a you want to tell the
the expression value of this we're back
to the scholarsity and integral
um and uh so this can be calculated by
uh well usually called the weak
contraction
um so uh let me is this
um some of uh or any equivalent
um
uh with contractions well I mean that
we're contraction I'll explain that in
the listening
uh so
um uh I again write down this sequence
of the cues but let me just write a few
more you I'll uh whatever
okay so an example of the weak
contraction is uh if I
uh if I uh connect a pair of excuse like
so you can like any pair I want but I
cannot uh but every time I can talk with
you that the spirit is gone then that's
repeat so I'll break down for your
contract this with with that maybe this
with with that so this is a possible
with instruction
and every queue has to be contracted if
you have odd number of Cubes the result
is zero it's only even number two
um and uh and there's no order in the
contraction so so if I can track you
enter Q out qn I'm not ordering uh and
also there's no order with back to the
different instructions so so
um so there's no other uh if I contract
this Q and The Q Alpha first uh and qm
with new gamma second or the other
around it makes no difference so
um I'm only going to sum over distinct
ways of the contraction which I mean by
all the in the equivalent
uh and the claim is that uh so for
everyone contraction
so this is a notation so every weak
contraction this is going to be uh
defined to be uh this a inverse
and then the current exam
uh and uh and you see that uh this
applies uh to the previous case right so
in this example uh if you know that we
can talk a rule then you don't have to
bother with the picture and just say
this could cover this let's connect this
and then there are two more in
equivalent contractions and you're done
uh and this one's General okay so so
that's that's
how you will generally calculate the
value of Armature number of Cubes
inserted in this legality integral
okay so all of this is just doing Simple
gaussian integrals nothing two things
uh so uh first of all you'll agree that
there'll be 24 charts
it's four factorial
uh and uh so uh it'll be one over eight
qualified by 34 terms contributions
uh so for example I can swap these two
legs
because you know I can connect this to
that uh listen to this that that's one
permutation against what these two and
then as well
go home and do all kinds of examples
yes um
you know the version of this will need
to uh you know what's uh I guess
preparing for that okay
um uh any other questions yes
uh in fact do you mean the Innocence
uh no I don't know there's no
restriction right so so in fact we saw
an early example of this day in verse
was actually only 9-0 with that and M
are equal uh so it's a general depends
on you know yeah so so we're going to
depend on whether a inverse Matrix is
so I'm saying that for Arthur n and M
this contraction the result is by
definition a inverse but inverse
measures of age the NM entries
that doesn't matter
let's quickly explain the rule version
of Harley Davidson
yes so so I have more cues yes uh so one
concussion is this uh the second
contraction
is uh one two three two to four and then
I can have uh one to four a two to three
yeah and that's it there's nothing more
again there's no other specifications so
that's it
and so the sixth which is another
example
I
always gonna be
uh uh once you go to this formula this
is a true formula okay you can try to
prove this if you want I'm not I'm not
going to to prove on the board but you
can try to improve it but in this
formula there is no contrary character
there's no coefficient one because the
sum of like once we get before oh uh uh
wow there's a number of terms you can
calculate it's not well it's not for
factorial because this is this example
it's a three okay
it's generally going to be you know
whatever uh and I like them to
annotations if the N factorial divided
by some one yeah it's whatever it comes
out that explains this exponential so so
it's going to work out
uh but you know you are invited to to to
try to improve it yourself but I I won't
bother with that proving this I'll just
assert this is true you have to trust me
uh any other questions yes
what other things there's no other
things right here
got 20 points
that's right these are only three things
but it cannot be anything else
uh all right
um okay so um now we're going to
generalize all of this which are for
finite dimensional intervals in this
discussion uh to uh the function of
lowercase
um this translation is more or less
straightforward but uh
um the only thing I want to explain is
uh
there's a little bit of detail that that
you're not care about you can't they can
do the normalization
how this works so we're not now I'm
going to generalize
uh to uh gaussian uh
functionalism
um so that means uh instead of
considering some n dimensional Vector Q
uh this Q Vector is going to be replaced
by let's say a few of Tau in our
mechanical model but this could be much
more General but now I'm just
considering function of one variable
because this variable being the we can
protect the time for an answer
uh right so so you should think of this
as
uh viewed
as a vector so this is a function and we
want to do this as a vector in the
linear
price
of
real functions
uh subject to some additional assumption
on functions which I will not uh
uh go beyond the level of mathematical
rigor I'm working with right now so I
would not specify that I'll just say
that q q account uh you know it's a
function Tau but we're going to view
this as just like this Cube as a vector
in a linear space of functions so for
example uh those qns remember we started
with QR pal but I'll respect the
functions on this uh interval between
minus p and t and we said that the
boundary conditions for the Q to vanish
at end points so that was made the
function so what some of the space the
functions on that interval the
advantages the advantage of the
endpoints the unlatchment function in
the cube I can expand on some arbitrary
Fourier bases and then got this Q an
coefficients but the Q and Company
tribute the QA coefficients has nothing
but the compressions of some Vector with
a personal basis uh Vector that you
choose on this infinite dimensional
space of functions okay so so that's
that's uh
um and so uh now this uh uh SC is going
to be whatever action uh the the
euclidean action they're going to be
working with
um I'm going to specialize onto the
bottom of this in a moment and this J
dog with q
um it's going to be replaced by uh while
Q is going to be a function now so this
dot product which sum over the indices
is going to be something like an
integral so let me write something like
integral of the Tau uh J or Tau Tau so
this J Vector is now also going to be
replaced by a function
um
and this that product is going to be
replaced by some intervalent Tau J Tau Q
attack but anyway uh you should be minus
the J still is just a bookkeeping device
that we're gonna eventually take a
derivative or function with back to J
and extract the correlation
functions of Interest
foreign
we're going to try to put the action in
the form of this Q transpose a q uh so
this a which with the Matrix The Matrix
a that appeared I guess I erased it uh
is now a linear operator
on the space of uh functions in the one
variable here in this example uh right
so a before it was it was a matrix the
multiply on the back to give you another
Vector so now a is a function between
another function so uh
now and it gives you something uh so far
in the
in the example of the
harmonic oscillator
I'll say another example
uh this was a very simple uh
[Music]
operator it's going to be minus the
accounts where the Omega Square
why do this we remember what was that
what was in the exponent so but
the harmonic
because
uh an action integral detail one half of
the cloud Q it's worth plus Omega
squared this one lower than you
including action so all I'm doing is I'm
integrated by Parts by parallel right
this is you now one half to do in front
q1 L minus the without squared plus
Omega squared
and this is what I call a
right so um
so so a that is replaced Now by a
completely defined in this way just
adapt it to the example of the harmony
operator uh but we're going to be
interested in a inverse
so the inverse Matrix of a which uh
whose analog here will be the inverse
awkward so what is the inverse operator
uh well
um
uh what's the inverse what's the inverse
of that differential operator
uh well uh by definition it should be a
convenient it doesn't have to be
differential operator because they're
they're more General linear operational
function than they can be derivative
they also do it works
um so all you have to be is something
that if you act with a again it gives
you back here uh so uh in fact this the
answer is that it's integral you now
Prime of sound G Count top Prime
Q of prime uh where G is some function
uh well I guess I'm using this same
notation as this G earlier but this
paper right is the difference in this no
at this point there's not a lot of
relationship and the brilliant G even
though there won't be a relation and you
see later but so far there's no
connection this is just some function
all right so what does this do you have
to obey well first of all this is
currently leading
um but you need a property that if you
act on this again
a few
um this year this will be
um
square plus Omega squared
at least if you can assume you can
exchange the order of the derivative by
this integral which you can use it at
some nice convergence property event
um all this requires is uh is that this
thing icon G which should give you the
Delta function
that is you want uh minus the power
squared plus Omega squared I know g l
Prime is Delta function
foreign
the boundary or an Infinity but we'll
come to that in a bit but the G has to
at least obey this property
where this uh well this statement to
make sense but there's a universal and Q
should be uh
um okay
so
um now
uh
uh so the thing we're going to be
interested in
uh is uh is is
represent values like like this
but more generally if you have more
through instructions but as you might
expect uh you know this is going to be
calculated by the same weak contraction
rule so actually uh all you can do is to
figure out what is the single weekly
track and why isn't all that you know
how we can do this for arbitrary number
two insertions
this one
well we've already encountered this but
now let's do it in a in a more uh
Elegance uh manager
uh so let me write this as a
uh so I'm going to use a shorthand
notification for this so this I'm just
going to write this one half above Q uh
in a product with paid Q uh so um by
this I just made a q Tau integrated
against a I can't hear whatever
so so this is just a location
um
uh by the way uh from now I'm going to
set H bar uh
um
thank you
q a one two
uh divided by
which is
okay uh so now uh you might say oh we
already know how to how to do this the
result is a inverse n and M but what is
n what is M what you meant to say it's
requested by Prime but uh
so this doesn't quite work okay so you
have to be very careful with that uh
with the normalization uh strategy
speaking if you want to really follow
repeat the previous derivation and apply
to this case you have to describe an
integral of steps
um but you have to worry about is this
measure factor which is the decimal uh
that's more step of course so so uh if
you keep track of that you can derive
the correct answer uh but um for the
purpose of clarity of expedition I'm
going to uh give you a shortcut
um and um
without having to go through all their
steps so I'm going to describe that
trick so uh let's look at this numerator
here
um so I'm going to rewrite the numerator
in the following way so that's going to
be written as integral BQ uh I guess no
one two
um uh so
um
due to the uh minus one yeah remember
this was the Italian
thank you
um so I've got a cue of pal one here pal
two uh but I'm going to write the Q of
Taiwan in the Holy way we're going to
write q a one importantly
uh
as
um minus a inverse actually
um B by B Q of a lot
uh so you see what that is do well this
is a function of derivative so so in
this box are derivative hits on this
Cube we can do the icon this Q right on
this Cube then on the first Cube I'm
just gonna get minus one have a cube
if I pack on a second the result
actually will be the same by the
integration by parts on this operative a
okay
um so
so the result of this function
derivative I can have this exponent uh
is just going to give me it's just going
to pull down from the exponents uh the
two terms the factor one half okay
cancel minus uh AQ and so that kinds of
the case is minus I'll get back to Q so
you think what
okay so so so so this expression here is
the same as the numerator
it's just a numerator
all right
um and um
um uh and a simple trick I'm going to
apply is that uh you know
um
this whole thing
can be used as the first order
differential operator on the cubes
at least in this case uh in the Galaxy
integral the measure is simple enough
that there's a transmission very
consumed again so it's very important
part so instead of this acting on that
is equal to minus of this
so by the functional integral by part uh
I just get this I can that so I have
principle DQ from e to the minus the
action uh then I get minus the two minus
signs okay so we'll just get a inverse
um
d by d q L1
Q down two
and then this function here it is just
by definition delta of Tau y minus Tau
two and if I act on that with a inverse
going to that formula just plug in the Q
of Tau Prime in the Delta function the
result of this is uh so anyway
is equal to this partial function uh
times so the expanded value here
expression value here this whole thing
is just going to be equal to a g
over Tau one
so it's a a inverse
um
foreign
[Music]
to get to the answer just using the
general property of an integration by
parts at the functional integral level
um and that's the result of this
experiment value which is the same as
the contraction the one you have that
can calculates arbitrary
number of students that's very important
so so this will from now replace this
paper calculation we did at the
beginning of the lecture where we had to
detected finally everyone take some
limit that was the pain and this is a
much quicker way to get to the end
um I I haven't showed you
bottom gear
now what is this economic Q by
definition is the other function this is
right so so the result is a inverse
actually on a function with the function
the function is Delta of power minus L2
that would be the variable
foreign
okay
information